<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>
<!-- generated by https://github.com/cabo/kramdown-rfc version 1.6.27 (Ruby 3.1.4) -->
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-kcs-tvr-requirements-latest" category="info" submissionType="IETF" tocInclude="true" sortRefs="true" symRefs="true" version="3">
  <!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 3.17.0 -->
  <front>
    <title abbrev="tvr-requirements">TVR (Time-Variant Routing) Requirements</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-kcs-tvr-requirements-latest"/>
    <author fullname="D. King">
      <organization>Lancaster University</organization>
      <address>
        <email>d.king@lancaster.ac.uk</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="L. M. Contreras">
      <organization>Telefonica</organization>
      <address>
        <email>luismiguel.contrerasmurillo@telefonica.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="B. Sipos">
      <organization>JHU/APL</organization>
      <address>
        <email>brian.sipos+ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2023" month="May" day="24"/>
    <area>Routing</area>
    <keyword>Time-variant</keyword>
    <keyword>Routing</keyword>
    <keyword>Mobility</keyword>
    <keyword>Requirements</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>Time-Variant Routing (TVR) refers to the calculation of a path or subpath through a network where the time of message transmission (or receipt) is part of the overall route computation. This means that, all things being equal, a TVR computation might produce different results depending on the time that the computation is performed without other detectable changes to the network topology or other cost functions associated with the route.</t>
      <t>This document introduces requirements where TVR computations could improve message exchange in a network.</t>
    </abstract>
    <note removeInRFC="true">
      <name>About This Document</name>
      <t>
        Status information for this document may be found at <eref target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-ietf-tvr-requirements/"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
        Discussion of this document takes place on the
        Time Variant Routing Working Group mailing list (<eref target="mailto:tvr@ietf.org"/>),
        which is archived at <eref target="https://mailarchive.ietf.org/arch/browse/tvr/"/>.
        Subscribe at <eref target="https://www.ietf.org/mailman/listinfo/tvr/"/>.
      </t>
      <t>Source for this draft and an issue tracker can be found at
        <eref target="https://github.com/danielkinguk/tvr-requirements"/>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t></t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="conventions-and-definitions">
      <name>Conventions and Definitions</name>
      <t>The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL
         NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
         "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be interpreted as
         described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they
         appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
      <t>Specific terms used within this document are as follows:</t>
      <dl>
        <dt>Model:</dt>
        <dd>The universe being modeled, which defines a parameter space.</dd>
        <dt>Entity:</dt>
        <dd>A single separable item within the model. Each entity has a stable identity which is time-invariant.</dd>
        <dt>Property:</dt>
        <dd>A single attribute of an entity which is used to parameterize that entity. The notion of a property is not time-variant, the property always exists within an entity but its value may be time-variant.</dd>
        <dt>Property Value:</dt>
        <dd>The specific value of a property, both as a planned state within the schedule timeline and as a realized state in wall-clock time.</dd>
        <dt>Schedule:</dt>
        <dd>The method of parameterizing time-variance intrinsic to a time-variant model. The parameters of a schedule are within the state space of the model.</dd>
        <dt>Schedule Time:</dt>
        <dd>An idealized timeline within a time-variant model over which entities and property values may change without a difference of state in the model itself. The notion of schedule time is intrinsic to the model.</dd>
        <dt>Wall-Clock Time:</dt>
        <dd>The true timeline, measured in some time scale by some local ticker. The notion of wall-clock time is extrinsic to the model; even non-time-variant models allow for changes over wall-clock time, just as different model states rather than a change <em>within</em> the model itself.</dd>
        <dt>Time Instant:</dt>
        <dd>A single instant of time, consistent with the concepts of date-time in <xref target="RFC3339"/>.</dd>
        <dt>Timeline:</dt>
        <dd>A possibly bounded interval of time, consistent with the concept of a period in <xref target="RFC3339"/>.</dd>
        <dt>Subsequent:</dt>
        <dd>A time instant which is later in a timeline than some reference time instant.</dd>
      </dl>
    </section>

    <section anchor="overview">
      <name>Overview of Time-Variant Networks</name>
      <t>Existing Internet routing techniques maintain end-to-end connected paths across a network. Routing mechanisms exist to recover
         connectivity and resume normal traffic forwarding as the topology changes. Occasionally, optimisation of routes may also be
         requested, especially post-topology changes due to disruptive events. However, there are a growing number of use cases where
         changes to the routing topology are an expected part of network operations. In these scenarios, the pre-planned loss and
         restoration of an adjacency, or formation of an alternate adjacency, should be seen as a non-disruptive event.</t>

      <t>Time-Variant Routing (TVR) refers to calculating a path or subpath through a network where the time of message transmission
         (or receipt) is part of the overall route computation.  Therefore, a TVR computation might produce different results
         depending on the time that the calculation is performed without other detectable changes to the network topology or other
         cost functions associated with the route.</t>

      <section anchor="scheduling">
        <name>Resource Scheduling</name>
        <t>Planned resource scheduling will be required for various scenarios; these include networks with mobile nodes, such as
           crewless aerial vehicles and orbiting satellite constellations. In these scenarios, links are lost and re-established
           as a function of the mobility of the platforms. Furthermore, link activity might be restricted to certain times of the
           day in networks without reliable access to power, such as networks harvesting energy from tidal, wind, and solar
           resources. Similarly, network traffic might be planned around energy costs or expected user data volumes in networks
           prioritising green computing and energy efficiency over data rate.</t>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>General Temporality</name>
        <t>
This section covers different aspects of how temporality applies to any potential TVR information model.
Each aspect is roughly independent and informs how a model can choose to include temporality in its parameter space.
        </t>
        <section anchor="time-scope">
          <name>Scope of Time-Variability</name>
          <t>
One aspect of any time-varying model is the scope of what may be time-variable.
Two extremes of this aspect are:
          </t>
          <ul>
            <li>A model which is completely time-invariant, which while there is still a notion of time it has no affect on any of the model entities.</li>
            <li>A model in which every entity has some kind of schedule applied.</li>
          </ul>
          <t>
It is expected that an application of time-variability to real world data models will keep some entities within the model time-invariant and allow scheduling of other, specific entities.
          </t>
          <t>
Another aspect of any time-varying model is the granularity of state to which a schedule can be applied.
Two extremes of this aspect are:
          </t>
          <ul>
            <li>A model where one single schedule applies to the entire universe (<em>i.e.</em> indicating when the time-variant entities are valid or invalid).</li>
            <li>A model where every property of every entity can be scheduled independently. This is the temporality model of <xref target="AIXM"/>.</li>
          </ul>
          <t>
It is expected that an application of time-variability to data models will fit within these extremes, possibly applying a schedule to each entity indicating when that entity is valid or invalid, or applying a schedule to groups of properties within the entity (while leaving other properties time-invariant).
          </t>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>Time Horizon</name>
          <t>
In an idealized model the schedules will apply indefinitely far in the past and the future, but in a realizable model with both processing and storage limitations there will need to be a time horizon within which the model applies and outside of which the model has no meaning.
In some cases this horizon will be intrinsic to the model itself, with an explicit model parameter indicating the horizon.
In other cases the model may allow indefinitely-large schedules but the processing of the planning timeline is bounded to limit resource needs.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>Time Precision</name>
          <t>
Different time-variant models will require different granularities of planning time, either because of limitations or assumptions about wall-clock time or because of requirements within the modeled domain.
It is up to specific models to define the precision of time values and the required accuracy and precison of wall-clocks which implement the schedules.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>Validity in a Schedule</name>
          <t>
Within a single schedule over the planning timeline there will likely be a need to have multiple discrete intervals of validity over absolute schedule time.
The time instants at which a schedule is invalid indicate an undefined property value, so it is important for a model to be able to accomodate multiple schedules as necessary to ensure that some properties can have values at all times.
          </t>
          <t>
A model which restricts itself to a single interval of validity could run into difficulties over a long enough time horizon and would need to resort to having multiple model entities represent the same modeled "thing" which can lead to confusion and inefficiency.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>Periodicity in a Schedule</name>
          <t>
Separate from the concept of intervals of validity in absolute schedule time, there can be a need to model repetitive states in a concise way.
One way to model a periodic change of state is to combine a set of absolute time intervals with a periodic parameterization (duration valid and duration invalid); this is the mdoel of <xref target="AIXM"/>.
          </t>
          <t>
A model which does not include the notion of periodicy within a schedule could be used in situations where discrete intervals of validity are needed to handle periodic state changes which is neither storage nor processing efficient.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>Continuity in a Schedule</name>
          <t>
A schedule which includes a sequence of time intervals needs to ensure that the interpretation of those intervals in the schedule timeline does not leave any "gaps" at the interval boundaries.
For that reason, it is important that the model uses half-open intervals of time so that time-adjacent intervals leave no gap.
In keeping with the terminology of <xref target="RFC3339"/>, intervals are bounded by their "start" and "end" instants.
It is <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> that any time-varying model use schedules with intervals closed on their start time and open on their end time.
This behavior lends to the interpretation, in the schedule timeline, that the scheduled state takes effect at an interval's start and continues until the subsequent state.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>Time-Overlap and Priority</name>
          <t>
In an ideal situation a model would be guaranteed by design to contain only contiguous and non-overlapping schedules for each time-variant scope.
In a realized model this kind of invaraint might not be enforcable or might lead to overly complex schedule structures.
One way a model can handle this is to establish a concept of schedule priority, where some intervals of the schedule timeline contain overlapping schedules for the same properties and only the highest-priority schedule applies.
When priorities are allowed by a model, it enables the concept of an "overlay" where a long-duration state can be temporarilly (in schedule time) superseded by a short-duration state.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>Property Value Interpolation</name>
          <t>
When a schedule is applied to an entity in a way which is more <xref target="time-scope">granular</xref> than just indicating when that whole entity is valid or invalid, the model needs to consider how individual properties are to be treated between scheduled instants.
Some of the possibile behaviors are:
          </t>
          <dl>
            <dt>Zero-order hold:</dt>
            <dd>
From the instant a scheduled value applies to a property until the subsequent-in-schedule-time value supersedes it.
This is simple from a logical standpoint, but discontinuties in the value over schedule time could cause issues with the model itself.
For some models, though, the constant values between change instants are actually beneficial by allowing the entire timeline to be compressed into a sequence of discrete state-change instants.
This is the behavior implied in models such as <xref target="AIXM"/>.
            </dd>
            <dt>Linear interpolation:</dt>
            <dd>
At the instants of time defined in the schedule the property takes the exact values, but between those instants the property is interpolated linearly over time.
This results in a state that is continuous over time, which is beneficial for some kinds of model but also means that there is no simple discrete sequence of states.
            </dd>
            <dt>Higher-order or spline interpolation:</dt>
            <dd>
Higher order interpolations can result in properties that vary over schedule time in ways that are more or less beneficial to different types of models.
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <t>
Regardless of the types of interpolation used, a model can choose to apply interpolation globally or per-property.
Since different properties represent different physical or logical metrics of a network it is expected that different types of interpolation will be needed for different represented quantities.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>Changes to Model State</name>
          <t>
Separate from how a time-variant model can contain a schedule timeline within the model state, a model design will need to consider how changes to the model state itself (over wall-clock time) are handled.
This aspect is actually not specific to a time-variant model but is important to consider in this context.
          </t>
          <t>
Two extremes of this aspect are:
          </t>
          <ul>
            <li>
A model which can only be changed wholesale, superseded by an entire new model state.
This is easy to keep consistent but has inefficiences of storage and transport if the model state is to be shared or exchanged between real entities.
            </li>
            <li>
A model which has an intrinsic notion of fine-grained superseding changes, possibly scoped to individual entities, individual schedules, or more complex groupings.
            </li>
          </ul>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="topologies">
        <name>Topologies</name>
        <t>
The primary entities of a topological network model, as realized in <xref target="RFC8345"/> and similar predecessors, are nodes and unidirectional links, with a secondary entity representing the "termination point" for each side of a link at a node.
Following the concepts described in <xref target="scheduling"/> these are the entities to which an intrinsic schedule can be applied.
        </t>
        <section anchor="nodes">
          <name>Nodes</name>
          <t>
When a schedule is applied to a node the granularity <bcp14>SHALL</bcp14> at least be at the individual node.
In cases where the properties of a node have time-variable values the model <bcp14>SHALL</bcp14> define an interpolation method, either globally or per-property.
          </t>
          <t>
A node is just a named entity in Layer 3 <xref target="RFC8346"/> and Layer 2 <xref target="RFC8944"/> topologies.
Schedules on a node <bcp14>SHALL</bcp14> be used to indicate the validity of the entire node or changing properties of that entity.
When a schedule indicates that a node is not valid for a schedule time instant, that validity <bcp14>SHALL</bcp14> apply to all of its termination points and links as well.
This logic allows a schedule to represent, for example, the expected power-on state of a node at a specific layer.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="termpoints">
          <name>Termination Points</name>
          <t>
When a schedule is applied to a termination point the granularity <bcp14>SHALL</bcp14> at least be at the individual entity.
In cases where the properties of a termination point have time-variable values the model <bcp14>SHALL</bcp14> define an interpolation method, either globally or per-property.
          </t>
          <t>
A termination point is associated with an IP address in Layer 3 <xref target="RFC8346"/> and a MAC address in Layer 2 <xref target="RFC8944"/> topologies.
Schedules on a termination point <bcp14>SHALL</bcp14> be used to indicate the validity of the layer-2/3 interface represented by the entity or changing properties of that entity.
When a schedule indicates that a termination point is not valid for a schedule time instant, that validity <bcp14>SHALL</bcp14> apply to all of its links as well.
This logic allows a schedule to represent, for example, the expected power-on or administrative-enabled state of an attached network interface card (NIC) or virtual private network (VPN) endpoint.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="links">
          <name>Links</name>
          <t>
When a schedule is applied to a link the granularity <bcp14>SHALL</bcp14> at least be at the individual link.
In cases where the properties of a link have time-variable values the model <bcp14>SHALL</bcp14> define an interpolation method, either globally or per-property.
          </t>
          <t>
A link is associated with link metric properties in Layer 3 <xref target="RFC8346"/> and Layer 2 <xref target="RFC8944"/> topologies.
Schedules on a link <bcp14>SHALL</bcp14> be used to indicate the validity of the entire link or changing properties of that entity.
When a schedule indicates that a link is not valid for a schedule time instant, that validity <bcp14>SHALL NOT</bcp14> apply to its termination points and nodes.
This logic allows a schedule to represent, for example, the expected connectivity state, data throughput/rate, and latency/delay of a link.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>Network Layering</name>
          <t>
When a schedule indicates that an entity is not valid for a schedule time instant, that validity <bcp14>SHALL NOT</bcp14> apply to any of its associated overlay or underlay network entities.
The effects of scheduled administrative disabling or enabling of an entity at one layer do not imply a change in administrative enabled state at any other layer.
Likewise, the assigning of an address property at one layer does not imply the presence or absence of an address assignment at that same time instant for any other layer.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="routing">
        <name>Routing</name>
        <t>Existing routing techniques are not typically designed to handle potential connectivity, i.e., nodes and links
           scheduled to appear in the future. Therefore, the TVR Scenarios and use cases referenced and discussed in this
           document will be compromised of scheduled resources that are expected to appear in the future.</t>
        <t>However, even if some adjacency failures are predictable, others are not, including link failures and node outages.
           Therefore, any new technique or routing protocol extension for TVR enviroments must be capable of handling planned and unexpected
           resource losses.</t>
         <section anchor="constraints">
         <name>Constraints</name>
         <t>TBD</t>
         </section>
      </section>
    </section>

     <section anchor="tvr-use-case-requirements">
      <name>Time-Variant Use Case Requirements</name>
      <t>TBD</t>
    </section>

     <section anchor="operational-considerations">
      <name>Operational Considerations</name>
      <t>TBD</t>
    </section>

     <section anchor="security-considerations">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>TBD</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana-considerations">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This document has no IANA actions.</t>
    </section>

   <section anchor="contributors" numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>Contributors</name>

      <t>The following authors contributed significantly to this document:</t>
        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt="">
          <![CDATA[
   Zheng (Sandy) Zhang
   ZTE Corporation
   China
   Email: zhang.zheng@zte.com.cn
   
   Yuehua Wei
   ZTE Corporation
   China
   Email: wei.yuehua@zte.com.cn
          ]]>
       </artwork>
    </section> 
  </middle>

  <back>
  <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>	
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8174.xml"?>
	     <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-tvr-use-cases.xml"?>
      </references>
      <references title="Informative References">
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3339.xml"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8345.xml"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8346.xml"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8944.xml"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.I-D.king-tvr-ntn-challanges.xml"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.I-D.contreras-tvr-alto-exposure.xml"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.I-D.hou-tvr-satellite-network-usecases.xml"?>
        <reference anchor="AIXM" target="https://aixm.aero/sites/aixm.aero/files/imce/AIXM51/aixm_temporality_1.0.pdf">
          <front>
            <title>AIXM 5 Temporality Model</title>
            <author>
              <organization>EUROCONTROL and Federal Aviation Administration</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2010" month="September" day="15"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
    </references>
    </references>
 </back>
</rfc>
