<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>
<!-- generated by https://github.com/cabo/kramdown-rfc version 1.6.27 (Ruby 3.1.4) -->
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-kcs-tvr-requirements-00" category="info" submissionType="IETF" tocInclude="true" sortRefs="true" symRefs="true" version="3">
  <!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 3.17.0 -->
  <front>
    <title abbrev="tvr-requirements">TVR (Time-Variant Routing) Requirements</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-kcs-tvr-requirements-00"/>
    <author fullname="D. King">
      <organization>Lancaster University</organization>
      <address>
        <email>d.king@lancaster.ac.uk</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="L. M. Contreras">
      <organization>Telefonica</organization>
      <address>
        <email>luismiguel.contrerasmurillo@telefonica.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="B. Sipos">
      <organization>JHU/APL</organization>
      <address>
        <email>brian.sipos+ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2023" month="May" day="24"/>
    <area>Routing</area>
    <keyword>Time-variant</keyword>
    <keyword>Routing</keyword>
    <keyword>Mobility</keyword>
    <keyword>Requirements</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>Time-Variant Routing (TVR) refers to the calculation of a path or subpath through a network where the time of message transmission (or receipt) is part of the overall route computation. This means that, all things being equal, a TVR computation might produce different results depending on the time that the computation is performed without other detectable changes to the network topology or other cost functions associated with the route.</t>
      <t>This document introduces requirements where TVR computations could improve message exchange in a network.</t>
    </abstract>
    <note removeInRFC="true">
      <name>About This Document</name>
      <t>
        Status information for this document may be found at <eref target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-ietf-tvr-requirements/"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
        Discussion of this document takes place on the
        Time Variant Routing Working Group mailing list (<eref target="mailto:tvr@ietf.org"/>),
        which is archived at <eref target="https://mailarchive.ietf.org/arch/browse/tvr/"/>.
        Subscribe at <eref target="https://www.ietf.org/mailman/listinfo/tvr/"/>.
      </t>
      <t>Source for this draft and an issue tracker can be found at
        <eref target="https://github.com/danielkinguk/tvr-requirements"/>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t></t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="conventions-and-definitions">
      <name>Conventions and Definitions</name>
      <t>The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL
         NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
         "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be interpreted as
         described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they
         appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="overview">
      <name>Overview of Time-Variant Networks</name>
      <t>Existing Internet routing techniques maintain end-to-end connected paths across a network. Routing mechanisms exist to recover 
         connectivity and resume normal traffic forwarding as the topology changes. Occasionally, optimisation of routes may also be 
         requested, especially post-topology changes due to disruptive events. However, there are a growing number of use cases where
         changes to the routing topology are an expected part of network operations. In these scenarios, the pre-planned loss and 
         restoration of an adjacency, or formation of an alternate adjacency, should be seen as a non-disruptive event.</t>
         
      <t>Time-Variant Routing (TVR) refers to calculating a path or subpath through a network where the time of message transmission
         (or receipt) is part of the overall route computation.  Therefore, a TVR computation might produce different results 
         depending on the time that the calculation is performed without other detectable changes to the network topology or other 
         cost functions associated with the route.</t>   
         
       <section anchor="scheduling">
        <name>Resource Scheduling</name>
        <t>Planned resource scheduling will be required for various scenarios; these include networks with mobile nodes, such as 
           crewless aerial vehicles and orbiting satellite constellations. In these scenarios, links are lost and re-established 
           as a function of the mobility of the platforms. Furthermore, link activity might be restricted to certain times of the 
           day in networks without reliable access to power, such as networks harvesting energy from tidal, wind, and solar 
           resources. Similarly, network traffic might be planned around energy costs or expected user data volumes in networks 
           prioritising green computing and energy efficiency over data rate.</t>
       </section>
       <section anchor="topologies">
        <name>Topologies</name>
        <t>TBD</t>
         <section anchor="nodes">
         <name>Nodes</name>
         <t>TBD</t>
         </section>
          <section anchor="links">
          <name>Links</name>
          <t>TBD</t>
          </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="routing">
        <name>Routing</name>
        <t>Existing routing techniques are not typically designed to handle potential connectivity, i.e., nodes and links 
           scheduled to appear in the future. Therefore, the TVR Scenarios and use cases referenced and discussed in this
           document will be compromised of scheduled resources that are expected to appear in the future.</t>
        <t>However, even if some adjacency failures are predictable, others are not, including link failures and node outages.
           Therefore, any new technique or routing protocol extension for TVR enviroments must be capable of handling planned and unexpected 
           resource losses.</t>   
         <section anchor="constraints">
         <name>Constraints</name>
         <t>TBD</t>
         </section>
       </section>
    </section>

     <section anchor="tvr-use-case-requirements">
      <name>Time-Variant Use Case Requirements</name>
      <t>TBD</t>
    </section>

     <section anchor="operational-considerations">
      <name>Operational Considerations</name>
      <t>TBD</t>
    </section>

     <section anchor="security-considerations">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>TBD</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana-considerations">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This document has no IANA actions.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
  <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>	
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8174.xml"?>
	     <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-tvr-use-cases.xml"?>
      </references>
      <references title="Informative References">
        <?rfc include="reference.I-D.king-tvr-ntn-challanges.xml"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.I-D.contreras-tvr-alto-exposure.xml"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.I-D.hou-tvr-satellite-network-usecases.xml"?>
    </references>
    </references>
 </back>
</rfc>
